Guide to the Emanuel Celler Collection BCMS.0017
Brooklyn Collection
Emanuel Celler Collection
1912-1981
1950-1980
Brooklyn Collection
Celler, Emanuel, 1888-1981
BCMS.0017
27.6 Linear feet in 1 carton, 19 oversize boxes
Materials created and collected by Congressman Emanuel Celler, who served Brooklyn's 10th, 11th and 15th districts for nearly 50 years. Items include speeches, correspondence, photographs and legislative materials.
Biographical Note
Emanuel "Manny" Celler was born on May 6, 1888 on Sumner Avenue, where his family owned a whiskey business called Echo Spring. The business eventually failed and Celler's father took a job as a door-to-door wine salesman. Celler graduated from Boys' High School in 1906 and enrolled at Columbia University where he studied Law. While at Columbia, Celler went to class in the morning and sold wine in the afternoon and evening, a job he inherited after his father's sudden death. He graduated from Columbia and passed the New York bar exam in 1912. Celler quickly found work as an attorney and eventually opened his own practice, which remained open even after he was elected to Congress.
In 1922 Celler was asked to run as the Democratic Party's nominee for Congress in the 10th District. Celler campaigned hard and won the election by just over 3,111 votes, becoming the first democrat to represent the district. After taking office he devoted himself to a number of issues including the repeal of prohibition and immigration reform. His first speech on the floor of the House was in opposition to the Johnson Immigration Act of 1924, which limited the number of immigrants admitted to the United States to two percent of the total number of individuals from each nationality living in the United States according to the 1890 census. The Act passed despite his efforts. During the 1940s he worked to allow larger numbers of Europeans fleeing World War II to enter the United States, calling Roosevelt's current policy "cold and cruel." His work on exclusionary immigration laws culminated in the Hart-Celler Act of 1965, which eliminated national origin as a basis for exclusion.
Cellar was a vocal opponent of the House Un-American Activities Committee and Joseph McCarthy, who he rallied against in a strongly worded speech delivered at the 1952 Democratic National Convention. He was also on the forefront of civil rights legislation, helping to write and pass the Civil Rights Act of 1964, the Civil Rights Act of 1968 and the Voting Rights Act of 1965. A strong supporter of Israel, he was honored by several Jewish organizations including with an honorary doctorate from Yeshiva University. Celler also received an honorary Doctor of Laws degree from Brooklyn College.
Celler served in Congress for almost fifty years and as Chairman of the House Judiciary Committee from 1949 to 1973. In the 1972 primary Celler lost in an upset to newcomer Elizabeth Holzman. After leaving office Celler returned to his law practice and to his home at 9 Prospect Park West. He died at the age of 92 on January 15, 1981.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of items created and collected by Congressman Emanuel Celler (1888-1981). Celler's research and writing on topics such as antitrust, immigration and copyright are included, as well as speeches delivered at events and honors. Celler also kept a small, handwritten appointment diary and book of collected jokes. Correspondence is both personal and professional, the bulk of which are from his last year in office and post-congressional life. His invitations to presidential inaugurations and White House events are also included.
Certificates include a copy of Celler's marriage license and an honorary Doctor of Laws degree from Brooklyn College. Academic hoods worn by Celler at the commencement exercises of Brooklyn College and possibly Yeshiva University are included. Clippings cover a range of topics concerning Celler's congressional activities. Clippings concerning Celler's death are housed in the Death and Memorial Services series. Photographs include both portrait and candid images of Celler and other political figures. A series of framed Acts and Resolutions with the signing pens are also included.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was donated by Emanuel Celler's daughter, Jane Wertheimer.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in nine series by type:
Series I: Writing and Speeches arranged alphabetically by topic or occasion.
Series II: Correspondence arranged by date. Items kept by Celler in a binder have been left in original order.
Series III: Degrees and Certificates arranged by type.
Series IV: Clippings arranged chronologically whenever possible.
Series V: White House Invitations arranged chronologically. Early non-inaugural items are foldered together.
Series VI: Death and Memorial Services arranged together in one folder.
Series VII: Photographs arranged by subject.
Series VIII: Art and Textiles arranged by type.
Series IX: Legislative Material arranged chronologically.
Related Materials
Articles about Emanuel Celler appearing in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle (1910-1955).
Brooklyn Biographical File: Emanuel Celler.
Celler, Emanuel. You Never Leave Brooklyn. J. Day Co. 1953.
Transcript of Oral history interview with Emanuel Celler, member of Congress from New York, 1923-73. c1981.
Antitrust law; Civil rights; Equal rights amendments; Legislators--New York (State); Presidents--United States--Inauguration; United States--Emigration and immigration--History--20th century; United States--Politics and government--20th century
- Series I: Writing and Speeches
  - Antitrust, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armenia, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce Honor, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ARMD, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Congressional Censors, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Copyright Revision, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diaries and Joke Books, circa 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Displaced Persons, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Double Taxation Laws, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Equal Rights Amendment, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Impeachment, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - India, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Arts and Humanities Foundation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Palestine, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Poetry and Sketches (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Prohibition, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Warsaw Ghetto, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1949-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Binder 1)
- Series III: Degrees and Certificates
  - Personal, 1912-1914 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Professional, 1953-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Professional, 1951-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Plaque from the Jewish Nazi Victim Organization (Box 3)
  - Plaque from United Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society Service (Box 3)
- Series IV: Clippings
  - Clippings, 1926, 1957-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clipping, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series V: White House Invitations
  - General White House Invitations, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Franklin Roosevelt Inauguration, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Harry Truman Inauguration, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - John F. Kennedy Inauguration, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series VI: Death and Memorial Services
  - Death and Memorial Services, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series VII: Photographs
  - Celler Family (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Office (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Neighborhoods (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Note
    Grand Army Plaza, Park Slope
  - Subseries 1: Portraits, Celler
    - Emanuel Celler Portraits (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Emanuel Celler Portraits (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries 2: Portraits, Not Celler
    - Cashmore, John (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Elath, Eliahu, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Smith, Alfred E. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Tarchian, Albert (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Wagner, Robert F. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Warren, Earl (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Wilson, Woodrow (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Wise, Stephen S. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Subseries 3: Group Portraits, Identified
    - Cardinal Cooke (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Clark, Ramsey (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Congressional Dinner Guests (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Craige, Tom (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Eighty-Sixth Congress Committee on the Judiciary, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Gandhi, Manilal, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Heuss, Bundespresident; Altmaier, Jacob (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Hooker, Robert; Vilfan Joza, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Johnson, Lyndon, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Keller, John W. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - McCormick, John (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - McCormick, Steve (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - National Federation of Women's Clubs, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Radhakrishnan, Sarvepalli, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Silver, Abba Hillel (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Walter, Francis; Keating, Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Group on Steps of Capitol Building (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 4: Group Portraits, Unidentified
    - Group Portraits, Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Group Portraits, Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series VIII: Art and Textiles
  - Bronze bust by Nathan Rapoport, 1960 (Object On Display)
    Currently on display in the Brooklyn Collection reading room.
  - Academic hood, Brooklyn College (Box 4)
  - Academic hood, possibly Yeshiva University (Box 4)
- Series IX: Legislative Material
  - Emanuel Celler Federal Building, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Pen that signed H.R. 5884, an Act to establish a uniform system of bankruptcy through-out the United States. Includes letter from Louis McH. Howe, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Pen that signed H.R. 8368, an Act to enforce the twenty-first amendment. Includes letter from M.H. McIntyre, 1936 (Box 6)
  - Pen that signed H.R. 4011, an Act to continue the functions of the Commodity Credit Corporation and the Export-Import Bank of Washington, and for other purposes. Includes letter from M.H. McIntyre, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Pen that signed the 1946 immigration quota. Includes photograph (Box 8)
  - Pen that signed H.R. 4233, an Act to provide for the naturalization of persons serving in the Armed Forces of the United States after 1953. Includes photograph (Box 9)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 137, an Act to amend the Clayton Act by granting a right of action to the United States to recover damages under the antitrust laws, establishing a uniform statue of limitations, and for other purposes, 1955 (Box 10)
  - Signing pen and a copy of Public Law 85-315, an Act to provide means of further securing and protecting the civil rights of persons within the jurisdiction of the United States, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Signing pen and a copy of Public Law 87-36, an Act to provide for the appointment of additional circuit and district judges, and for other purposes, 1961 (Box 12)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 87-664, an Act to authorize the Attorney General to compel the production of documentary evidence required in civil investigations for the enforcement of antitrust laws, and for other purposes, 1962 (Box 13)
  - Pen that signed H.R. 7193, an Act to provide for the striking of medals in commemoration of the fiftieth anniversary of the founding of the first union health center in the United States by the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union. Includes letter from Lawrence F. O'Brien, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 89-129, a Joint Resolution to provide for the development of Ellis Island as a part of the Statue of Liberty National Monument, and for other purposes, 1965 (Box 15)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 89-236, an Act to amend the Immigration and Nationality Act, and other purposes, 1965 (Box 16)
    Also known as the Hart-Celler Act.
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 90-158, an Act to amend sections 337 and 338 of the Bankruptcy Act and to add new section 339, 1967 (Box 17)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 90-198, an Act to extend the life of the Civil Rights Commission, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 90-338, a Joint Resolution authorizing the National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence to compel the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of evidence, 1968 (Box 19)
  - Signing pen and copy of Public Law 90-383, an Act to amend section 127 of title 28, United States Code, to define more precisely the territory included in the two judicial districts of Virginia, 1968 (Box 20)